Guide to the Carl Menger Papers, 1857-1985
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Carl Menger papers 1857-1985
Menger, Carl, 1840-1921
10 linear feet
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Durham, North Carolina 27708-0185
Carl Menger was an economic theorist and professor. Chiefly notebooks, notes, teaching materials, correspondence, biographical and personal material, and printed material (7500 items, 10 lin. ft; dated 1857-1985), relating to Menger's academic career, 1867-1920. The bulk of the collection consists of Menger's notes and revisions on economic and theoretical topics, and on his first major work, Grundsätze der Volkswirthschaftslehre.. Includes extensive material about money, the gold standard, and capital theory. Other topics include economic principles, jurisprudence, credit, property, philosophy, the nature of science, methodology, interest, research on political economy, and the classification of knowledge. Family papers relate to Anton and Max Menger. Letters to Menger are primarily from colleagues of the Austrian school of economists, especially Eugen von Bohm-Bawerk, Johannes Conrad, Eugen von Philippovich, Emil Sax, and Friedrich Wieser, concerning professional matters. Other correspondents include Friedrich A. von Hayek, Ludwig von Mises, Oskar Morganstern, Richard Schuller, Joseph Alois Schumpeter, and Knut Wicksell. The addition (02-220) (150 items, 0.40 linear ft.; dated 1855-1921 and n.d.) comprises letters, notes, postcards, and calling cards from Menger's brothers Anton and Max Menger as well as from distinguished Austrian, German, and other writers, artists, philosophers, jurists, historians, and politicians. Correspondents include Arthur Schnitzler, Henryk Sienkiewicz, Theodor Gomperz, Friedrich Jodl, Karl Kraus, and Otto Weininger. Materials in this accession are unprocessed.
RL.00887
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The papers of Carl Menger (1840-1921), economic theorist and professor, were donated to Duke University in 1987 by his granddaughter, Eve L. Menger.
Biographical Note
1840, February 23 Born, Neu Sandec, Galicia (then in the Austrian part of Poland)
1863-1871 Editorial and reporting posts on the Lemberger Zeitung, then on the Wiener Zeitung
1867 Doctorate in jurisprudence, University of Cracow
1871 Publication of Grundsätze der Volkswirthschaftslehre
1872-76 Habilitation and appointment as professor extraordinarius, University of Vienna
1876-78 Tutor and traveling companion to Archduke Rudolf, Austrian crown prince
1879 Full professorship, University of Vienna
1883 Publication of Untersuchungen über die Methode der Socialwissenschaften, und der Politischen Oekonomie insbesondere, which precipitated the Methodenstreit with the younger German Historical School
1884 Publication of Irrtimer des Historismus in der Deutschen Nationalkonomie, Menger's reply to criticism by Gustav Schmoller
1892 Joined the Austrian state commission on currency reform and the evaluation of a bullion standard
1903 Retired prematurely from his active professorship to devote himself entirely to research
1921 Died in Vienna
1923 Publication of a second edition of the Grundsätze edited by Menger's son Karl
Carl Menger was born in 1840 in Neu Sandec, Galicia, of well-to-do titled parents. His life followed a path typical for someone in a family of similar social and intellectual standing. His work as journalist, tutor to the crown prince, and professor marked his role as part of a flowering European intellectual elite.
After attending Gymnasium, he matriculated at the universities of Vienna and Prague, leaving school in 1863 for a position on the staff of the Lemberger Zeitung. He continued to hold a number of other reporting and editorial posts over the course of the next dozen years, ending with the Wiener Zeitung. The list of Menger's contributions to the press in later years attests to the ties he retained in this area.
In the meantime, Menger received his doctorate in jurisprudence from the University of Cracow and began his work on political economy. By 1871 he had begun the process of publication and simultaneously applied for full instatement on the law faculty at the University of Vienna. In his diary, Menger noted it was not without some difficulty that he achieved this goal in July of 1872. For the next several years he taught finance and political economy to an increasing number of students, both in seminars and lectures, while also contributing to the Wiener Zeitung.
In the fall of 1876, Menger was approached with a request to become tutor in political economy and statistics to the Crown Prince of Austria. The ensuing association lasted until the death of the prince in 1889 and brought the talented young economist in contact with politically and socially influential people throughout Europe and England. He made two tours with Crown Prince Rudolf, one throughout Europe, and a second to the British Isles. Menger's contact with the prince lessened after their travels and after the prince had successfully completed his examinations, but from Menger's diary entries it is clear he continued to benefit from this royal association, particularly in the area of university appointments.
With the exception of the short hiatus of a few semesters with the crown prince, Menger taught until 1903, when he retired early in order to devote himself entirely to research. He spent the majority of his professional academic career in Vienna, a city acknowledged as one of the premier cultural centers on the continent. His writings, like his background, are a window upon the mind and concerns of the late-nineteenth-century intellectual. Far from having a focused and narrow concern with a particular aspect of economics, Menger sought to define the discipline and science of (non-mathematical) economics and to place it within the broader context of intellectual inquiry. Although the last several decades of Menger's life may be quickly described as involved in teaching and research, comprehending the quality and quantity of his life's work presents a great challenge to contemporary researchers.
Collection Overview
The Carl Menger Papers span the years 1857 to 1985. Although the collection includes material from Menger's early professional life as well as some items from his brothers, Anton and Max, and his son, Karl, it is primarily composed of manuscripts and correspondence, 1867-1920, relating to his mature academic career. The contents are extremely dense and complex; they are also essential to an understanding of the mind of Carl Menger. Not only do the papers reflect Menger's mind, but they also document his own methods of work. He was a copious note-taker and read voraciously. He kept bound notebooks with reflections and excerpts from his current reading, especially in the early years when he was constructing the Grundsätze. Later he made notes and revisions on loose sheets, having some of them copied into a clear hand, and on those sheets, too, he made revisions. Menger also wrote directly in the printed text. For example, his papers include two copies of the Grundsätze (a third similar copy is in the Hitotsubashi University Library with the rest of Menger's library) with blank pages interleaved with pages of text. In each of these successively Menger made extensive notes and changes. Although it is frequently impossible to date his manuscripts precisely, one can get a sense of the development of his thought from this sort of progression with the help in some cases of holographic evidence.
The collection has been organized into series which reflect both Menger's style of work and his major areas of research. The series include: research notebooks; manuscripts and notes on economic principles, money, and methodology; teaching materials; correspondence; biographical and personal materials; related family materials; miscellany; and printed matter.
Menger's work on political economy and on the nature of his subject and its appropriate research method typify changes in the intellectual frontier in fin-de-siecle Vienna, and Europe as a whole. Some of Menger's most explicit thoughts on these subjects are evident in his lecture notes. Although he taught for over thirty years, the collection contains only a small amount of material from this aspect of his career. What one discerns from the lecture notes, however, is a personal sense of the teacher, and his high degree of moral commitment to his work. Menger clearly thought it important to articulate his thoughts on the distinction between political economy and jurisprudence--since that was the faculty in which he taught--and the method and aims of the discipline.
The bulk of the collection consists of Menger's notes and revisions on economic and theoretical topics. The series on general economic principles contains material relating to his first major work, the Grundsätze der Volkswirthschaftslehre, which he published in 1871. Despite the lack of a full-length coherent manuscript for this book, his background work can be discerned from a set of extensive notebooks he kept. These contain extracts of works Menger read, as well as his reactions and reflections. The range of works shows familiarity with classical authors, particularly Aristotle and Plato, through to his own contemporaries. He showed special interest in writers on law, political economy, and theories of knowledge, such as Grotius, Malthus, J. S. Mill, Ricardo, J. B. Say, Roscher, Descartes, Francis Bacon, Locke, Kant, Fichte, Hegel, and Savigny. Many of the notebooks date from the late 1860s and thus, in the absence of more explicit information from Menger about his development, serve the function of intellectual diaries. Early versions of the actual manuscript of the Grundsätze exist in fragmentary form, mostly heavily revised. A table of contents, dated 1870, provides a useful comparison for later revisions and schemas.
The collection contains extensive materials on the subjects of money, the gold standard, and capital theory. The work on money, which is some of the best ordered in the collection, Menger produced as an article for the second edition of the Handwrterbuch der Staatswissenschaften in 1990, with substantial revisions for the third edition in 1909. Yet even after the latter edition, Menger continued to make changes and notations. His work on monetary reform grew out of an appointment to an Austrian state commission on currency and the use of a single or double bullion standard. Newsclippings of the reports have been maintained in the printed matter series.
Although not direct concerns in the Grundsätze, capital and interest received much attention from Menger, particularly in his refutation of his colleague Eugen Bohm-Bawerk's work of 1885, Geschichte und Kritik der Kapitalzinstheorien. Holographic evidence suggests that after dealing with this subject extensively in the late 1880s, Menger did not return to it again until the second decade of the twentieth century, when he was no longer teaching. At that point he resumed his considerations of capital and interest but looked additionally at credit and property.
The series in the collection which seems most opaque and less easily classified by subject deals with Menger's speculations and theories about the goals and methods of research, specifically for political economy, and the classification of knowledge. The appearance of the Untersuchungen über die Methode der Socialwissenschaften, und der Politischen Oekonomie insbesondere in 1883 provoked sharp criticism from Gustav Schmoller, representing the younger German Historical School. Their dispute came to be known as the Methodenstreit. In the following year, Menger replied to Schmoller with his Irrtimer des Historismus in der Deutschen Nationalokonomie. After this, Menger published no further major works, although he continued to produce articles and book reviews for many years. His notes and manuscripts indicate that his research came to an end only with his death.
Menger's professional contacts with respected colleagues such as Emil Sax, Eugen Philippovich, and Bohm-Bawerk demonstrate that although he refused to publish further, he did not work in isolation. The incoming correspondence shows a lively exchange of information about university teaching and politics, news of the profession, and current research. Letters also refer frequently to works of others in the profession. Few drafts of Menger's own letters exist in the collection. A large proportion of these seem to be addressed to Bohm-Bawerk.
Subject Headings
Economists -- Austria; Economics -- Study and teaching -- Austria; Jurisprudence; Money; Credit; Gold standard; Interest; Capital; Property; Research; Philosophy; Science; Bohm-Bawerk, Eugen von, 1851-1914; Conrad, Johannes, 1839-1915; Philippovich, Eugen von, 1858-1917; Sax, Emil, 1845-1927; Wieser, Friedrich, Freiherr von, 1851-1926; Hayek, Friedrich A. von (Friedrich August), 1899-; Von Mises, Ludwig, 1881-1973; Morgenstern, Oskar, 1902-1977; Schuller, Richard, 1870-; Schumpeter, Joseph Alois, 1883-1950; Wicksell, Knut, 1851-1926; Menger, Anton, 1841-1906; Austrian school of economists; Menger, Max (Maximilian), 1838-1911
Contents of Collection
- Notebooks
  Contain excerpts from works on political economy, definitions of economic terms, philosophy, and the nature of science. Many entries are Menger's notes from readings, but approximately one-third are his own musings and reactions. Not all notebooks are dated, but they fall into two periods, one in the late 1860s, the second in the 1910s. Arranged chronologically.
  - Nos. 1-4 (Notebooks, 1867-1868) (Box 1)
  - Nos. 5-9 (Box 1)
  - Nos. 10-14 (Box 1)
  - Nos. 15, A, B. 16, 17A (Box 1)
  - Nos. 17B-20, 3 unmarked (Box 1)
  - Geflandügelte Worte, ca. 1867-1868 (Box 2)
  - Excerpts to 1899 (Box 2)
  - Unmarked, 1870 (Box 2)
  - 5 Notebooks (Box 2)
  - 6 Notebooks, c. 1909-1918 (Box 2)
  - 4 Notebooks, 1917 (Box 2)
  - 6 Notebooks, 1918-1920 (Box 2)
  - 8 Notebooks, 1903, 1917-1919 (Box 3)
  - 4 Notebooks, 1902-1919, 1919/1920 (Box 3)
- Notes on Economic Principles (Box 3)
  Copious revisions of the Grundsätze (unpublished during Menger's lifetime), arranged according to topic in roughly the same order as presented in the first edition of the Grundsätze; some notes from Karl Menger along with sections he chose to include in the posthumous second edition of the Grundsätze. Other topics covered extensively in this series are capital and interest, particularly in relation to Böhm-Bawerk's theories, and ownership and property.
  - Excerpts from English works; Sonnenfels and others (Box 3)
  - Misc. Notes (Box 3)
  - Excerpte (Box 4)
  - Theoretisches Repertorium, 1867 (Box 4)
  - Grundsätze, table of contents, 1870 (Box 4)
  - Einleitung. Zusammenhandangende aber nicht abgeschlossene Darstellung der theor. 1889 (Box 4)
  - Einleitung I (Box 4)
  - Gandüter Wesen (Box 4)
  - Gandüter (Box 4)
  - Oekon. Gandüter (Box 4)
  - Arten der Gandüter (Box 5)
  - Ad Gut (Grundsätze, Ch. 2) (Box 5)
  - Gut (Box 5)
  - Wirtschaft, ca. 1888 (Box 5)
  - Complicationen der menschlichen Wirtschaft (Box 5)
  - Gangbarkeit; Wirtschaft und Gandüter (Box 5)
  - Wirtschaft (Box 5)
  - Wirtschaft (Box 5)
  - Subjekte der Wirtschaft (Box 5)
  - Wirtschaft, 1907. Includes material on Bedürfnisse. (Box 5)
  - Wirtschaft, 1906-1907. Also, material for introduction to a 2nd edition. Dates from c. 1899 (Box 5)
  - Wirtschaft; includes material on etymology, Gandüter, and an introduction to a 2nd edition. (Box 6)
  - Volkswirtschaft (Box 6)
  - Vermögen (Box 6)
  - Notes on goods and needs, includes material from 1st edition and Karl Menger's notes for 2nd edition. (Box 6)
  - Notes on value, human demand, needs (Box 6)
  - Bedürfnisse (Box 6)
  - Misc. notes on needs, c. 1912-1916 (Box 6)
  - Bedürfnisse, 1918 (Box 6)
  - Bedürfnisse, 1907 [1898-1910], (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Bedürfnisse, 1907 (Box 7)
  - Wert der: (1) Grundstücke und Bodennutzungen; (2) Arbeitsleistung (Box 7)
  - Wert (Problemestellung der Productivität des Capitals) (Box 7)
  - Ad subjektive Wertlehre (Box 7)
  - Wert (Box 7)
  - Wert; Tausch (Box 7)
  - Tauschhandel (Box 7)
  - Theorie der Preises (Box 7)
  - Notes on monopoly (prices) (Box 8)
  - Freihandel und Schutzzoll, 1908 (Box 8)
  - Diverses [ad Preislehre], 1908 (Box 8)
  - Waare (Box 8)
  - Münze; Scheidemünze; Urkundengeld (Box 8)
  - [Einkommen]: Die Problemestellung (Box 8)
  - Einkommen (Box 8)
  - Einkommen/Wert (Box 8)
  - Erwerbswirtschaft und Aufwandswirtschaft (Box 8)
  - Kritik der Smith'schen Einkommens Analyze (Box 8)
  - Capitalseinkommen (Box 8)
  - Capitalbegriffe (Box 8)
  - On Capital (Box 8)
  - Capital: Erspartes Einkommen (Box 8)
  - Misc. notes on etymology of terms, capital and interest (Box 8)
  - Notes on exchange, capital, etc. [on back of R.R. map of Central Europe] (Box 8)
  - On: Vermögen, Capital, Einkommen (Box 8)
  - On origin of term, capital; Wert; Vermögen (Box 8)
  - Capital: Gegen Böhm (Box 8)
  - On Böhm-Bawerk's theories: transcripts by A. Zlabinger (Box 8)
  - Typescript on capital (Box 8)
  - On Capital (Box 8)
  - Capital (Box 9)
  - Böhms Capitalzinstheorie (Box 9)
  - Material on Böhm, including a draft obituary notice (Box 9)
  - Material on Zinslehre, 1879 (Box 9)
  - Notes on interest (Box 9)
  - Notes on production and interest (Box 9)
  - Theorie des Vermögenertrages, 1901 (Box 9)
  - On property and ownership (Box 9)
  - Gemein-Eigentum (Box 9)
  - Besitz-Eigentum (Box 9)
  - Grund Eigentum (Box 9)
  - Kritik ad Lotz, c. 1890s-1910s (Box 9)
- Notes on Money (Box 9)
  Contains revisions to Menger's article on money in the second and third editions of the Handwörterbuch der Staatswissenschaften. This section is arranged roughly in the order of the second edition article. Where possible folders have been labeled to indicate where the material would belong in either or both editions. Some of these manuscripts were used by Menger's son Karl in the second edition of the Grundsätze. There are also several folders on monetary reform, especially from Mengers's service on an Austrian government commission to reform the currency and evaluate its relation to bullion standards.
  - Geld, section 5-14 translated by A. Zlabinger (Box 9)
  - Transcripts of manuscripts by A. Zlabinger (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous notes, (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Diverses ad Geld (Box 10)
  - Excerpts on money (Box 10)
  - Ueber die Natur und die Funktionen des Geldes (Box 10)
  - Ueber die Entwicklung der Geldwirtschaft (Box 10)
  - Geld, 2nd edition (Box 10)
  - Geld, revisions to 2nd edition (Box 10)
  - Aufgabe der Theorie des Geldes (Box 10)
  - Gangbarkeit (Box 10)
  - Bisherige Lösungsversuche [über die Erscheinung des Geldes] (Box 10)
  - Entstehung des Geldes, 3 und 4. Aufl. (Box 11)
  - Ob Geld Ware [sei] (Box 11)
  - Juristische Geldlehre, revisions to 2nd ed. sec. X; 3rd ed., sec. II (Box 11)
  - Entstehung des Edelmetallgeldes (Box 11)
  - Vervollkommnung des Metallgeldes...; ad Münze; Scheidemünze (2nd ed., sect. III; 3rd ed., sec. IV) (Box 11)
  - Währung (2nd ed., sect. IV) (Box 11)
  - Beeinflussung des Geldwertes durch den Staat (Box 11)
  - Einfluss des Staates (Box 11)
  - Funktionen des Geldes (2nd ed., sect. V-VII; 3rd ed., sec. VI-IX) (Box 12)
  - Preismesser (2nd ed., sect. VIII; 3rd ed., sect. X) (Box 12)
  - Das Geld als Massstab des Tauschwertes, pt. 1 (2nd ed., sec. IX; 3rd ed., sec. XI) (Box 12)
  - Das Geld als Massstab des Tauschwertes, pt. 2 (2nd ed., sect. IX; 3rd ed., sec. XI) (Box 12)
  - Massstab des Tauschwertes; Entstehung des Irrthums, 1909 (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous notes, 1911-1915 with transcriptions by A. Zlabinger (concerns Tauschwert) (Box 12)
  - Begriff des Geldes, (2nd ed., sec. X; 3rd ed., sec. XII-XIII) (Box 12)
  - Bedarf an Geld, (2nd ed., sec. XI; 3rd ed., sec. XIV) (Box 13)
  - Differenzierung des Geldes (Box 13)
  - "Wertscalen" (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous Notes (Box 13)
  - Neue Parthien (Box 13)
  - Currency Reform, 1892 (Box 13)
  - Currency Reform, clippings (Box 13)
  - Currency Reform (Box 13)
  - Currency Report Notes (Box 13)
- Teaching Materials (Box 13)
  Includes lecture notes from several semesters and one folder of student papers on the term "capital". Arranged chronologically.
  - Seminararbeiten über Kapitalbegriff, etc. (Box 13)
  - Lectures ( Die Theorie und Praxis des Bankwesens. Erste Vortrag), 1872 (Box 13)
  - Lectures, c. 1884-1894(114, 115, 481) (Box 13)
- Notes on Methodology (Box 13)
  Notes and revisions for the Untersuchungen, material on the ensuing Methodenstreit, G. Schmoller, and Menger's subsequent refutation, Irrtimer; notes for the article on the Klassifikation der Wissenschaften and material refuting Wundt; many general notes and partial manuscripts, apparently for a book on methodology and the aims of research which would have included material on the inductive vs. deductive method and the importance of theory in research. Arranged topically.
  - Material on Irrthümer (Box 14)
  - Schmoller (Box 14)
  - Franz. Nationaloekonomie (Box 14)
  - Notes on Classical Economics (Box 14)
  - Untersuchungen, 1 p. (Box 14)
  - Die Frage über die Methode... from Juridicheski Westrik No. 12 (1884): 581 (Box 14)
  - Methode, 1876 (Box 14)
  - Methode Material, (2 folders) (Box 14)
  - Diverses ad Methode pt. 1 (Box 14)
  - Diverses [ad] Methode pt. 2 (Box 15)
  - Typed transcript of plan for work on method and other notes (Box 15)
  - Ad Methode (Box 15)
  - Misc. Notes (Box 15)
  - Grundrichtungen der Forschung (Box 15)
  - Etymologie/Philosophie (Box 15)
  - Schema für eine Classification der Wissenschaften überhaupt (Box 15)
  - Notes on Classification der Wissenschaften (Box 15)
  - Classification der Wirtschaft. Wissenschaften includes material on Erkenntnisziele der Forschung and die realistische Richtung der Forschung (Box 15)
  - Classification der Wissenschaften, c. 1892-1894 (Box 15)
  - Printed work on plants, 11 pp., concerned with classification (Box 16)
  - Verständnis und Voraussicht (Box 16)
  - "Gegen Wundts Auffassung der Wissenschaft", (2 folders) (Box 16)
  - "Mathematik: Ideele Richtung," c. 1898 (Box 16)
  - Erkenntnisziele/Richtungen der Forschung, (2 folders) (Box 16)
  - Material on directions of research, with special attention to "Deduction," 1890s (Box 16)
  - On Induction (Box 17)
  - "Induction," ca. 1899 (Box 17)
  - "Ueber Wesen der Methoden..." [Induction/Deduction] (Box 17)
  - "Empirismus in der deutschen Nationaloekonomie" [late 1890s], (2 folders) (Box 17)
  - "1. Empirische Gesetze; 2. Arten" (Box 17)
  - "Material ad Unzulänglichkeit des Empirismus" (Box 17)
  - "Empirismus, Realismus, Positivismus in deutscher Nat. Oek." (Box 17)
  - "Realistische Richtung..." (Box 18)
  - "Ob exacte realistische Theorien auf Geb. d. Tat. Erscheinungen mogl?" [c. 1890s] (Box 18)
  - "Realismus" (Box 18)
  - Realistische auch idealistische Richtung der ideologischen Forschung" (Box 18)
  - "Theorie...Realismus..." On Logik, (2 folders) (Box 18)
  - Kritik von Wundts Logik" (Box 19)
  - "Causalität," c. 1905-1914 (Box 19)
  - "Willensfreiheit; Ethik," c. 1904-1910 (Box 19)
  - Notes on free will; self consciousness, c. 1912- 1914 (Box 19)
  - Notes on role of value judgments in Wissenschaft (Box 19)
  - Moral im Handel, scattered pp. and notes (Box 19)
  - Notes on philosophical topics, c. 1907-1913 (Box 19)